"The Benefits and Side Effects of Ginseng"
Ginseng root is
a popular herbal medicine.
Like the word panacea,
ginseng's Latin name, Panax,
is derived from the Greek
for "cure-all."
It can extend the lives of fruit
flies and microscopic worms,
but not mice.
What about people?
Well, there have been more than
100 clinical trials
using various
ginseng formulations,
but the results
have been underwhelming.
A meta-analysis of randomized
double-blind
placebo-controlled trials
found ginseng did not appear
to significantly affect
the duration of illness
but did appear to reduce
the risk of developing
acute upper respiratory
infections in the first place.
Digging deeper, however,
the preventive benefit appears
limited to Asian ginseng,
which cut infection risk in half
compared to placebo,
as opposed to American ginseng,
that only reduced risk
16 percent,
which did not reach
statistical significance.
Asian ginseng can then be
further divided up
by processing method.
White ginseng is
Asian ginseng root
that's simply been
washed and dried,
whereas red ginseng is
the same root,
but undergoes an additional step
of steaming before drying.
Red ginseng is often used
for male erectile dysfunction.
While it doesn't appear to help
with female sexual dysfunction,
a meta-analysis of a half dozen
randomized controlled trials
found that 4 to 12 weeks
of 1.8 to 3 grams a day
of Korean red ginseng
can improve erectile dysfunction
compared with placebo.
58 percent of men experienced an
improvement in sexual function
compared to 20 percent of men
in the placebo group.
This may be due to an
improvement in artery function
demonstrated within three hours
after consumption.
Of course, this is assuming
there's actually ginseng
in your "ginseng."
Ginseng is
a multibillion-dollar industry,
and as such suffers from
intentional contamination
with cheaper filler substitutes,
some of which may not be benign.
If your quote-unquote
"ginseng" supplement
turns out to be just
powdered soybeans
then you've just
wasted your money.
But, for example,
if it's been spiked with
illicit horse painkiller,
it's worse than a waste.
A study of the more than 500
ginseng products
sold in a dozen countries
across six continents
found that 24 percent
were adulterated.
This is consistent with
so-called "immune boosting"
supplements in general.
A 2022 analysis found most such
products failed to match
what was on their labels.
Maybe it's good there's
no ginseng in your ginseng?
From an oxidative
stress standpoint,
American, Chinese,
and Korean ginseng
all have been shown
to acutely protect against
free radical-induced DNA damage
within hours of consumption,
but one longer-term trial
raised red flags.
Although four weeks
of Korean ginseng
reduced levels
of oxidative stress,
four months of American ginseng
(about a quarter teaspoon
a day of whole root powder)
caused an uptick in DNA damage.
Until it can be shown that
chronic intake of other ginsengs
aren't also DNA-damaging,
I'd recommend steering clear.
Approximately 10 percent
of users suffer from
what's been termed
ginseng abuse syndrome,
which manifests
as high blood pressure,
nervousness, sleeplessness,
skin eruptions,
and morning diarrhea.
Of course it may not actually
be from ginseng itself
but rather adulterants in some
supposed ginseng product.
What if you randomize people
to ginseng that's been
officially authenticated?
In a multicenter,
double-blind, randomized,
placebo-controlled safety trial,
a thousand people were
randomized to 2 grams a day
of red ginseng or placebo
for six months.
In the ginseng group, 345
adverse effects were recorded.
But the placebo group
had 389 adverse events.
Each of the top five
quote-unquote "side-effects"
were documented more often
in the placebo group.
Outside of a clinical trial,
though,
it's hard to know
what you're going to get.
Aside from
the abuse syndrome symptoms,
there have been case reports
of manic psychosis,
estrogenic effects,
and increased surgical bleeding,
and so some recommended ginseng
should be avoided
in those expected
to undergo surgery,
those with
a predisposition to mania,
estrogen-dependent disease,
hypertension,
or hyperthyroidism.